"Risks and Benefits of
Nicotinamide Mononucleotide (NMN), a NAD+ Booster"
Both NR and NMN have been shown
to have beneficial effects in rodents,
though they haven’t
been tested side-by-side.
Both precursors raise blood
levels of NAD+ in people
but similarly haven’t been pitted
head-to-head against one another.
One potential advantage
of NMN over NR
is that it may be more
stable in the bloodstream.
In mouse blood at least, within an hour,
most NR is converted into NAM,
whereas NMN levels remain steady.
You could also argue that NMN is better
because it’s a direct precursor of NAD+,
whereas NR first has
to be converted to NMN;
so, we might as well just
take NMN in the first place.
Ironically, the exact opposite
argument can also be made
based on the inability of NMN to
pass through cell membranes.
Structurally, NMN is just NR with
a phosphate group attached to it.
The phosphate charge prevents NMN
from passing in and out of cells;
so, to get inside a cell, NMN first
has to be converted into NR.
Then, once inside, the NR can turn
back into NMN and make NAD+.
So, if NMN first has to be converted
into NR for cell entry, the argument goes,
maybe you might as well
just take NR to begin with,
because there’s no
NMN transporter.
Or is there?
An NMN transporter was recently
described (at least in mouse intestine);
so, maybe NMN is
able to skip the NR step
and pass directly into cells
to make NAD+ after all.
However, the evidence that such a NMN
transporter exists remains controversial.
NMN boasts a long list of
rodent healthspan benefits,
but, unlike NR, has yet to demonstrate
an extension of mammalian lifespan.
What about in people?
There have just been a few human
NMN studies published to date.
One small study of healthy
middle-aged men
found that various single doses
had no apparent effect
on any of the measured variables,
including retinal eye function,
sleep quality, heart rate,
blood pressure,
oxygenation,
or body temperature.
A 12-week study of daily NMN supplementation
in middle-aged men and women
similarly found no significant
effects on any outcome,
including lean mass,
muscle mass, body fat,
blood sugars, cholesterol,
or insulin sensitivity.
NMN did boost blood NAD+ levels,
though they peaked after the first month
and then trended down
for months two and three;
so, there may have been an
adaptive drop in NAD+ synthesis
as was suspected with NR.
Like NR, NMN also fails to
raise NAD+ in muscle tissue.
One study evocatively entitled,
“Nicotinamide Mononucleotide Supplementation
Enhances Aerobic Capacity in Amateur Runners,”
tested three different doses of
NMN versus placebo for six weeks
among young and middle-
aged recreational runners.
Aerobic capacity was increased at one
ventilatory threshold, but not the other.
No overall benefit for aerobic
capacity or peak power
or any of another ten measures of
cardiopulmonary function was found.
If you measure enough things,
statistical outliers,
both positive and negative ones,
can just pop up as flukes.
For example, the researchers
noted significant improvement
in the single-leg stance test,
but the NMN had no significant effect on
any of the other physical function tests.
And upon closer inspection,
the apparent single-leg balance benefit
was only found in the middle-dose group
compared to the high-dose group,
because the high-dose group ended up
doing slightly worse compared to baseline.
No significant effect was found for
any of the doses compared to placebo.
A similar issue can be found in a 12-week
study of NMN supplementation in older adults.
The NMN company-funded
authors concluded
that NMN “improved lower limb function
and reduced drowsiness in older adults.”
But it failed to significantly
affect 16 additional measures,
including other tests of lower
limb function and fatigue.
There are so few NMN studies that this
kind of shotgun approach is understandable,
casting the widest possible net
for effects to be further tested,
but on their own cannot be presented
as convincing proof of efficacy.
All of the above NMN studies
were on healthy individuals.
What about testing NMN on those who
are already metabolically compromised?
Overweight or obese postmenopausal
women with prediabetes
were randomized to NMN
or placebo for 10 weeks.
NMN didn’t seem to affect
body weight or composition,
liver fat, blood pressure,
or a dozen other metabolic variables,
but it did improve
muscle insulin sensitivity,
though not enough to affect insulin levels
or short- or long-term blood sugar control.
This may be because insulin sensitivity
in the liver and body fat remained unchanged.
NMN also appeared to have no
effect on mitochondrial function
or muscle strength,
fatigability, or recovery.
In terms of safety, NMN shills speak of it as
being naturally found in fruits and vegetables,
but even the most concentrated sources
(edamame, avocado, and broccoli)
have over a hundred times less per serving
than the typical NMN supplement dose.
The same could be said for NR in milk
(human and otherwise).
There are safety evaluations for NMN
on rats and dogs, but unlike NR,
supplemental doses of NMN have yet to
be shown as safe for human consumption.
There are rodent studies
showing that NMN
may have negative metabolic
consequences compared to placebo,
but the most serious concern
is nerve degeneration.
The accumulation of NMN
in nerve cells is toxic.
Since NR is converted into NMN,
this is a major concern for
NR supplementation as well.
The type of nerve damage,
axon degeneration,
is a major contributor to a variety
of neurodegenerative disorders.
Blocking an NMN-synthesizing enzyme
appeared to help damaged neurons in vitro,
protection that’s abolished
by adding NMN back,
and adding an enzyme that chews up
NMN was also found to be protective,
further supporting a theory of degenerative
effects of accumulating NMN.
However, clinical effects
remain theoretical,
as these adverse effects have only been
demonstrated in fish, mice, and petri dishes.
Of course, NMN supplements may not
even have NMN in the first place.
ChromaDex, which sells the rival
supplement Tru Niagen (a form of NR),
claims to have tested the 22 NMN brands
with the highest market share on Amazon
and found that most had
virtually no NMN at all.
Ironically, many of the apparently fake
NMN products displayed quote-unquote
“certificates of analysis” and carried
hundreds or thousands of positive reviews.
Evidently, only 3 out of 22 were found to contain
as much NMN as advertised on their label.
Of course, ChromaDex isn’t
above being shady itself;
it’s been accused of making
hyped false claims for Tru Niagen
by both the FDA and the
Better Business Bureau.
In short, NR has been demonstrated
to be relatively safe but not effective,
and neither safety nor efficacy
has been established for NMN.